<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><?xml-stylesheet type="text/css" href="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/code/pfs.css"?><TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The history of the life and death of Pope Joane who was elected to the papacy, an. 855, under the name of Johannes Anglus of Mentz in Germany : published as an advertisement to all papists / faithfully collected and asserted by H.J., Gent.</title>
            <author>H. J.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 30KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 9 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2016-02">2016-02 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">B24888</idno><idno type="EEBO-CITATION">31355299</idno>
  <idno type="VID">205881</idno>
  <idno type="EEBO-PROQUEST">2240889671</idno>
  
            <idno type="STC">Wing J14</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">31355299</idno>
            <availability><p>This keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above is co-owned by the
    institutions providing financial support to the Early English Books Online Text Creation
    Partnership. This text is available for reuse, according to the terms of <ref target="https://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/"> Creative Commons 0 1.0 Universal
    licence</ref>. The text can be copied, modified, distributed and performed, even for commercial
    purposes, all without asking permission.</p></availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt><relatedItem type="facs" target="https://data.historicaltexts.jisc.ac.uk/view?pubId=eebo-e"/>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. B24888)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 205881)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1740:39)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The history of the life and death of Pope Joane who was elected to the papacy, an. 855, under the name of Johannes Anglus of Mentz in Germany : published as an advertisement to all papists / faithfully collected and asserted by H.J., Gent.</title>
                  <author>H. J.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 16 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for F. Coles ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1663.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Bodleian Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,363 texts created during Phase 1 of the project have been released into the public domain as of 1 January 2015. Anyone can now take and use these texts for their own purposes, but we respectfully request that due credit and attribution is given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Full documentation of the original data capture process is available from the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.
   All versions of the texts are now archived and freely available for download. See <ref target="https://textcreationpartnership.org/faq/#faq05">the TCP Download FAQ</ref>
   for detailed information. The TEI P5 versions are also freely available from the <ref target="https://github.com/textcreationpartnership">TCP Github repository</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp" matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)" replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char" matchPattern="(.+)" replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term type="corporate_name">Catholic Church --  Controversial literature.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Anti-Catholicism --  England.</term>
               <term type="topical_term">Papacy.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-12 </date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson </label>Sampled and proofread </change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-04 </date>
            <label>Alexis (Ali) Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited </change>
         <change>
            <date>2015-03 </date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion </change>
      <change><date>2021-05 </date><label>lb</label>TEI P5 conversion </change></revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:205881:1"/>
            <p>THE HISTORY OF THE LIFE and DEATH OF <hi>POPE JOANE:</hi> Who was elected to the Papacy, <hi>An.</hi> 855. Under the name of <hi>Johannes Anglus</hi> of <hi>Mentz</hi> in <hi>Germany.</hi> Published as an Advertisement to all Papists.</p>
            <p>Faithfully collected and asserted by <hi>H. J. Gent.</hi>
            </p>
            <figure>
               <figDesc>depiction of Pope Joan</figDesc>
            </figure>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed for <hi>F. Coles,</hi> at the Lamb in the <hi>Old Baily.</hi> 1663.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="history">
            <pb facs="tcp:205881:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:205881:2"/>
            <head>THE HISTORY Of the LIFE and DEATH of <hi>POPE JOANE,</hi> &amp;c.</head>
            <p>THE Nativity and Genealogy of some emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent persons, whose Actions and Fortunes have rendred them Famous or Infamous to future Times, are not unlikely compared to great Rivers, whose springs and Rises are most commonly unknown, or very uncer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain, because of those indiscernible conveyances and sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terraneous hidden passages, and the unobservablenesse of those little Brooks and Rivulets, that concurre to make up their swollen Channels; (one Reason why some choice men are challenged by several Countries to derive thence their Life and Originals) Besides the remarkable result of some persons greatnesse, by strange and secret progres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sions, do like a deluge or inundation carry all things so before them, beyond any reparation or recovery, and are of so sudden violence, that they leave the World ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in wonder and amazement at their effects, then afford any inquisition or possible knowledge of their Causes.</p>
            <pb n="4" facs="tcp:205881:3"/>
            <p>This Woman, or <hi>Sybilla Pontificia</hi> will appeare to be one of those grand Incognito's, as to any particulars of her Parentage and Extraction; for had she been possibly to be known, who and whence she was, it had been im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>possible she should have been what she was. It will suf<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sice to say, that by the agreement and consent of many Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish Writers, who first broached this story themselves (as shall abundantly hereafter be declared and manifested in their several Testimonies hereunto added) and cannot be taxed or charged with Heresie or Schisme, being writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten long before <hi>Luthers</hi> Reformation; She is named by that Masculine Appellation she took and assumed to her self (like Knight Errants that change their former name when they commence their Martial Atchievments) up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the beginning of her Mercuriall and Learned adven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures.</p>
            <p>So that she is known before her advancement to the Papall Dignity, by the name of <hi>Johannes Anglus,</hi> or <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>glicus Moguntinus, John English</hi> of <hi>Mentz,</hi> a City in <hi>Ger<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>many</hi> standing neer the River of <hi>Rhine,</hi> the chiefe seat of one of the Ecclesiastical Princes Electors of that Empire; who is stiled and denominated of this place, well worthy of the Birth it gave to this spirituall Female Potentate; though by this name, some Writers have been erroneously induced to change her Country, and to ascribe her birth to <hi>England.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>She is conceived as by presumptuous conjectures it may be maintained, to have been born about the year of the Incarnation 810, or very near thereabouts, of very mean Relations, but of a very great and active Spirit, surmoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting the weakness &amp; natural desidiency &amp; unpromptitude of her Sex: obliged to the special kindnesses of <hi>Minerva,</hi> whose illustrious Graces were abated and dulled with the joint influences of <hi>Venus;</hi> whose maligne conjunction and interposition spoyled all, and made this Queen of <hi>Sheba</hi> after all her refearches and travels for Wisdome, a Concubine and a Strumpet.</p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:205881:3"/>
            <p>Her Friends necessities not able to maintain and sustaine her body, much lesse Furnish and Replenish her mind, which before her puberty longed insatiably for the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of knowledge, gave her occasion to bethink her selfe of removing from that unhappy and injurious condi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of her residence with her Friends, into another more favourable and Hospitall place, and to resolve to that purpose to Travel and seek out such a convenience, where she might attaine her impatient desires of being ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>complished in all the learned Sciences.</p>
            <p>She was grown to some maturity, when she acted this deliberation and resolution to effect; a young man her Lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver, or rather <hi>Paramour</hi> offering his Company and kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nesse to the expedition; and thereupon she determined to disguise her self under the Counterfeit of the male Sex, and took the name abovesaid, and so Accoutred and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>companied began her Journey; which after much wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dring and peregrination, terminated at last at <hi>Athens,</hi> once the great and famous Lady and Mistresse of all Literature and newly then restored to some degree of those perfecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, for which in former times she was most deservedly celebrated and famed.</p>
            <p>The Ruins of Antiquity (to which the Papall Right &amp; opinions are beholding to for most of their Traditions, and therefore not to be Argued by them in this Case a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainst the received Authorities for it) have left no exact in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stances of her Conversation in this Academy; nor indeed can further notice be taken or required of such persons of such Excellence and Consummate qualities then by the most notable and eximious Conspicuity and Demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stration thereof, which gives credit like the Summe and gross of great and wonderful actions, to their small and gradational rises. But because this <hi>Athens</hi> story is made a grand exception and refutation of such a thing as <hi>Pope Joane,</hi> in the conclusion of this transcript and endeavour, that and other objections shall be answered.</p>
            <pb n="6" facs="tcp:205881:4"/>
            <p>This must be in the <hi>Interim</hi> asserted, that this <hi>Joane</hi> was a great and sudden proficient in all the Studies of that place; nor is it thought she ever attained to them by any Magick (of which without the cavil of any Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stant, some Popes have been Condemned; as namely, <hi>Syl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vester</hi> the second, whose Character as not so immediately necessary to this work in hand may be forborn) but by the course and ordinary method of the place, though by the unusual extraordinary felicity of her parts, Nature and Ingenuity.</p>
            <p>But this debonarity of her intellectuals was not defaeca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted and freed from the soyls and pollutions of her natu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rals and morals; the Records of her being in this place are not altogether silent what Acts she kept in this Uni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>versity with her <hi>Enamourato,</hi> though how she past from the Dignities and Honours here (as perhaps infamed and se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cretly withdrawn hence to avoid publique scandal) is not manifestly and evidently described.</p>
            <p>But that such a person came to <hi>Rome</hi> from <hi>Athens,</hi> from the <hi>Dame</hi> to the <hi>Empresse</hi> of the world (not to say from the Matron to the Prostitute) it will be no difficulty to evince; and that this <hi>Pope Joane</hi> did sit in Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Chaire, and performed all the Offices of that pretended Suprema<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy during that Papacy will be as little; and when we have settled her in that <hi>Chair,</hi> it will be no incongruous complement to bring her to <hi>Bed.</hi> And therefore we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>take our selvs to Testimonies, wherein following my Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thors Rule, I will use some part of their own Language in the Original Latine, and because the verity thereof depends upon number of Authentique witnesses (of their own party too,) I will not grudge the Reader my trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, nor deceive him by any designe; and first we will mention the names of all such Historians or other Writers that do maintain there was such a Pope as <hi>Joan,</hi> and then those of the Papal side, who oppugne and deny it.</p>
            <p>The maintainers of it are <hi>Marianus Scotus, Sigebert, Gote-fridus, Viterbiensis, Johannes de Parisiis, Martinus Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lonus,
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:205881:4"/>Petrarch, Boccace, Ranulphus Cestrensis, Johannes Lucidus, Alphonsus E Carthagena, Theodoricus de Niem, Chalcocondilas</hi> a <hi>Grecian</hi> Writer, and <hi>Wernerus Rolerink, Platina,</hi> (the chief and most resented and quarrelled) <hi>Palmerius, Nauclerus, Sabellicus, Trithemius, Volateran, Bergomensis, Schedel, Laziardus, Fulgosus, Textor,</hi> an Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stle Written by the Univerfities of <hi>Paris, Oxford,</hi> and <hi>Prague,</hi> to all at <hi>Rome, Mantuan, Crantius,</hi> and <hi>Charanza,</hi> and a number more of the Papistical Faction of all Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons: in short, <hi>Onuphrius</hi> himself, the great and first oppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ser of this Truth, confesseth; <hi>Multos &amp; magni nomini viros, Historiam hanc suscipere, eam quoque vulgo veram ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>istimari;</hi> that a great many men, and of great Fame doe receive this story, and that among the vulgar it is believed for true.</p>
            <p>The other Antagonists besides this <hi>Onuphrius</hi> a Fryar (who writ in One Thousand five Hundred sixty six, &amp; was the first Champion of them all, though almost Seven Hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred years after the prank was plaid) were no lesse then Cardinal <hi>Bellarmine,</hi> Cardinal <hi>Baronius,</hi> and one <hi>Fleri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mundus</hi> a <hi>French-man,</hi> a fine quirking fellow, whose dis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>putes like his Country Fashions, were as gay and pretty, so vain and ridiculous; but when the two great Cardinals, as any the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> can boast of, applied them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>selves to the stresse of the Controversie, we may be sure something more then ordinary engaged their appearance; <hi>Nec deus intersit nisi dignus vindice nodus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Come we now to the matter of fact, and because <hi>Platina</hi> in his lives of the Popes, an Historian of good Credit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong themselves, being counted a most Learned man by <hi>Trithemius,</hi> hath fairly and equally delivered the story, we will shew it in his words—<hi>Johannes Anglicus ex Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guntia oriundus malis artibus,</hi> &amp;c. <hi>Pontificatum Adep<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tus est, mentitus enim sexum cum faemina esset,</hi> &amp;c. the whole English was thus,—<hi>John English born at</hi> Mentz, <hi>got the Popedome, as men say, by evil Means; For he dissembled his Sex being a Woman indeed, and when she was very young
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:205881:5"/>she went to</hi> Athens <hi>with a Scholar who was in Love with her, where by hearing of good Readers, all good Learning she profited so well, that when she came to</hi> Rome, <hi>she had few fellows, but never a one her better. Now by reading and disputing learnedly and wittily, she got so much credit, that upon</hi> Pope Leo <hi>the Fourth his Death, she was chosen in his room (as</hi> Martian <hi>writes) by common consent.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>But within a while after she proved with Child by one of her own servants, and though she carried all closely for a time, yet at length as she went to</hi> St. John Laterans, <hi>be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween the</hi> Theatre, <hi>called the</hi> Collosses <hi>and</hi> St. Clements, <hi>she fell in Travel, and was delivered of a Child, (a Boy) and dyed in the place (others add she was also buried under that stone or monument of this disgrace) which was in the second year, first moneth, and fourth day of her Raigne, and she was buried without any Solemnity.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let not the Reader wonder at this her Assumption to the Mitre by reason of her Learning, for in that age very little sufficed the whole Conclave, and a bigger place then that, the whole world, for a Pedant Grammarian, passed then for a <hi>Sophy,</hi> and <hi>ABC</hi>'s were almost Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles; Nay <hi>Bellarmine</hi> in return of this story was not afraid of this happy luxuriancy, as to confess it in a more critical and curious age, by way of Droll, upon Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> that the Church (meaning of <hi>England</hi>) had got a Woman also to her <hi>Head.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I omit other Confirmations of this Truth, onely I shall particularize that she succeeded <hi>Leo</hi> the Fourth, in the year 855, and was succeeded By Pope <hi>Benedict</hi> the Third, in 858. which answers the time above mentioned of two years and some moneths, and supplies that place which the Papists have endeavoured to continue from <hi>Leo</hi> to <hi>Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nedict,</hi> though they justle out a Pope <hi>John</hi> by number the Eighth, (which name this <hi>Joane</hi> borrowed, as the Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pall Custom is upon their Election) and instead of a Four and Twentieth, of that name will not reckon but a three &amp; twentieth; imputing this their false reckoning, to the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piety
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:205881:5"/>of <hi>John</hi> the Twelfth, whose story we avoid; Onely thus much in Honour to the Name may be added, that the reason why <hi>Joane</hi> and other her Successors chose this name, was for this reason out of the New Testament— <hi>There was a man sent from God whose name was</hi> John; but sure there was never a Woman of that name had any mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion. But I will not too far anticipate my matter.</p>
            <p>For to return, <hi>Joan</hi> having by her Learning, and the Fame she had raised of her self by her disputations in the Schools, (whether the Nobles and great Personages resor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted) two years together, (a rarity in those dayes, as before) ascended the Chaire, did with no lesse gravity, seeming prudence and Authority, as well as Piety, behave her self to a general good esteeme and respect; She Consecrated and made Prelates, She ordained Presbyters and Dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cons; She Administred the Sacraments, and Finally all the Offices that pertained to the pretended High Priest, as came in her way during the short time of her Raign, she executed in every respect; and this <hi>Cornelius Agrippa,</hi> a man much Commended by Pope <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth, writ in a book of his solemnly priviledged by the Emperour <hi>Charles</hi> the Fifth.</p>
            <p>And this had been no great scandal to the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> who yet deny this to be true, and call for an ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count of her Transactions, with the Emperour or any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther Christian Prince; (as it was then the Popes Fashion to intermeddle with Temporal Affairs, and to inaugu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate and Confirme Christian Potentates) but her Raign was so short, that no such occurrence happened no more then in other Popes times, as <hi>Anastatius,</hi> &amp;c. Withal <hi>Joan</hi> had other private business to mind, which might take her off from busying her self in those wrangling mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and angry Debates and Disputes about power and jurisdiction. She had mancipated her self to sensuality and <hi>Cupids</hi> Dominion, to the loving embraces of her own
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:205881:6"/>Chamberlaine, whom she more minded then all the Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narchs in the world. I forbear out of respect to the Ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerable Dignity of St. <hi>Peters</hi> Chaire, to mention her libi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinous converse with that fellow any further, leaving them in those abominable secrets, which need a night, and the darkness of oblivion to conceale and abolish them.</p>
            <p>It will suffice to the Ingenious Reader, that she was im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnated by this fellow, and no other person made pri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vy to the burden of her Belly, which through her ignorance, or want of right Computation, or some preci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitatancy of nature delivered it self in her pompous pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession from the <hi>Vatican,</hi> to St. <hi>John</hi> of <hi>Lateran:</hi> but with such pain and speedy Torment, that the Mitred Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther died instantly thereof, and the Heir to the Popedome left it to her Successors at the same instant, at the old rack rent of <hi>Simony.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Papists here again cavil at the unlikeliness of this story, for that none but aged persons are elected to this dignity, when they have exceeded the years within which this teeming may be supposed, and that by the smoothnesse of her Face she might likewise have been discovered; to the first it is answered, that several Popes have been ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cted under the Age of Forty, as <hi>Leo</hi> the Tenth, as <hi>Gregory</hi> the Eleventh, and <hi>Boniface</hi> the Ninth, <hi>John</hi> the Twelfth, <hi>alius</hi> Thirteenth, <hi>Benedict</hi> the Ninth; as to the second, it was in those times the Fashion for the Clergy to shave themselves: and as men by shaving may make themselves look like Women, so Women by often shaving, may make themselves look like men, and therefore there was no rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>son they should suspect her for want of a Beard.</p>
            <p>All the City upon news of this strange accident, were in amazement, but the Clergy recovering themselves out of the stun and perplexity thereof, caused her to be buried in the same place instantly, whereafter a Marble Image was set up as a Monument thereof in the same place where she miscarried; which monument was likewise to be seen within these few years, even in <hi>Pius</hi> the Fifth his time:
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:205881:6"/>representing a Woman in Childbed, with a Boy or Infant new born, which the said <hi>Pius Quintus</hi> threw into the <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber,</hi> upon pretence, that it cumbred the street: but in truth that he might extinguish the Memory of that shamefull Fact, and this a Jesuite hath acknowledged, one <hi>Elias Has<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sen Muller,</hi> in his History of the Order of Jesuits, and of their Father and Mother. The like Image was set up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mong the rest of the Images of the Popes, in the renown<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Church of <hi>Siena</hi> (the birth place of this Pope <hi>Alexan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> the Seventh) in <hi>Italy,</hi> and was to be seen there within lesse then Sixty years, (but thrown down by Pope <hi>Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> the Eighth) which the Bishop of the place would not suffer to be defaced, at the last repayring of the Church, though the Jesuits did earnestly press and request him to deface it; The like is in pictures in several Romish books.</p>
            <p>Now because of that Marble Image standing in one of the chief streets of <hi>Rome;</hi> the Popes when they go in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cession, refuse to go through that street in detestation of the Fact, and go further about; though to slur this re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>marque also, the Papists say it is because that street is little and winding, and is not roomy enough for the Popes great Train in such Solemnities: but that's a meer shift, for as soon as ever by going into narrower lanes and circumam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bulation, the Pope hath left the place of that Image be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hind him, he turns into the same street again, and proceeds directly in his way.</p>
            <p>But of further evidences of the Truth hereof, the Chair whereon the Pope is set immediately after his Nomination and Election in the Conclave of the Cardinals is none of meanest; It is a Chair made like a Close Stool, wherein he then sits before publication is made of his Assumption to the papacy, which the lowest Cardinal Deacon, (whose office it is) underfeels to try if the Pope have Male Genitals, and upon his being certified thereof by attrectation of them; he cries out to the rest — <hi>Mas nobis Dominus est, i. e.</hi> we have a Man to our Lord; so justly fearful are they to have the same trick put upon them again.</p>
            <pb n="12" facs="tcp:205881:7"/>
            <p>This they likewise triflingly think to evade <hi>Florimon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> saying, that the Pope sits therein, not in a Corner, but in the great Church of St. <hi>Lateran,</hi> whether all the World almost comes to see him, where he is attended by the whole Colledge of Cardinals, and whereat there are ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny Embassadours of Kings and Princes, and so denyeth the prebation and Experiment made in the said Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clave; and further they alledge, that his sitting in that Chair, is to put him in mind that he is not God but Man, in as much as he stands in need of a <hi>Close-stool,</hi> as well as others: but no doubt there are more obvious and plai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner admonitions to be made use of to that purpose; as King <hi>Philip</hi> of <hi>Macedon</hi> had a Boy, who every morning constantly saluted him with this Note, <hi>Remember thou art Mortal;</hi> but that this disastrous and disgraceful accident could by no common ordinary Memento, be reduced and hinted to their exactest care and inspection.</p>
            <p>As for their other gloss of <hi>Bellarmines</hi> own framing: that the Pope is set on such a Stool, to signifie how he is raised from base Estate to supreme Honour, it is a meer fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacy, for the Popes for many years since this <hi>Pope Joane</hi> have been chosen for the most part out of the Colledge of Cardinals: And the Cardinals Estate is not so base, as that he who from thence is advanced to the papacy, can be truely said to be taken in any sort from off a Close<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stool; For they are generally Princes Fellowes, (and our <hi>Cardinall Woolsey,</hi> who was not ashamed to prefix his own name before the Kings, loudly speakes as much,) and Pope <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> affirmed, that the Height and splen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dour of a Cardinalship is equal to the Regall Dignity; wherefore unlesse some better Reason can be given, why the Popes are set on such a stool, which all popish Writers cannot but acknowledge: it must remain for certain, that in former times it was for proof of their Humanity, upon the accident aforesaid.</p>
            <p>All that hath hitherto been said hath been from their own Authorities. I omit what our <hi>John Bale,</hi> and <hi>Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bert
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:205881:7"/>Barnes</hi> and other forrain reformed Writers have writ on this subject, this being the sum of all, for little more is recorded of her Life. I must omit likewise what other animadversions, exceptions and quarrels the Romanists make upon every of the aforesaid passages thereof, as that there were no schools at <hi>Athens,</hi> whether she is said to have resorted for learning, no more then at <hi>Rome,</hi> where it is said she taught publickly, all which are learnedly and with great reason refuted by that judicious Controversiary, Mr. <hi>Alexander Cooke.</hi> Fain would the <hi>Romans</hi> be informed of her parentage, which no question in that ignorance, that clouded the world in that age, they made it little la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour to suppress and hide it themselves; but they may very well to their satisfaction and resolution in this point be contra-interrogated, who was the first Father of Pope <hi>Higinus,</hi> or <hi>Denis,</hi> whose Genealogies and Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trey could not be found, as likewise <hi>John</hi> the Nineteenth, <hi>Ʋrban</hi> the Fourth was begotten by a Cobler, <hi>John</hi> the Twenty second of a Botcher, <hi>Benedict</hi> the Eleventh of a Laundress, <hi>Benedict</hi> the Twelfth of a Miller, <hi>Sixtus</hi> the Fourth of a Marriner, <hi>Adrian</hi> the sixth of a Brewer, <hi>Sixtus Quintus</hi> of a Swineherd; <hi>Alexander</hi> the Fifth confessed he had no Friends, nor never saw any such; and finally there is nothing more omitted in Histories, then who were the Popes Fathers.</p>
            <p>They will indeed confesse, that all this smoke that hath been raised was not without some Fire; for when they perceived they could not overthrow the notoriety of this story, they cast about how to elude it; and therefore they say, that great Lies arise out of some Truth, for that Pope <hi>John</hi> the Twelfth, whom they confesse to have been ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>traordinarily addicted to Women, among other Wenches that he kept had one called <hi>Joane,</hi> who was all in all with him, and ruled the Roast: now the people perceiving what hand she had over him, termed her Pope, and des<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pised him: whereupon arose this slander of a Pope <hi>Joan;</hi> this was reinforced and seconded by another, that the
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:205881:8"/>people had him so much in derision for this effeminacy, that they changed his name, and called him <hi>Joan;</hi> Both which shadows of Excuse or Extenuation have discovered a most shameful story to the reproach of the papacy, and yet of no purpose, effect or advantage to this false sugge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stion; A suggestion leud enough in the Authors, but the substance of it far more leuder in the Actors.</p>
            <p>The Truth is, the papists would rather hear of a hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred Popes Nephews, though they be such as <hi>Casar Borgia</hi> was to <hi>Alexander</hi> the sixth, his own natural Sonne, titula<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>doed with that distanced degree of Relation, then hear of this pope Mother and her Son; which story to avoid they are driven to Feign, to Forge, to Cog, to play the Fools, and in plain English to lye all manner of lyes for the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vering their shame in this; <hi>Onuphrius, Harding, Saundert, Cope, Genebrand, Bellarmine, Bernardus, Florimondus, Papyrius Maso, Baronius, Parsons</hi> and divers others have joyned hand in hand, with purpose to carry this Cause away by strong hand, but are so entangled in it, that it is with them as with Birds in the Lime twigs, which stick faster in by how much they flitter the more to get out, as by this time it doth appear to all reasonable persons.</p>
            <p>And so we will dismiss this Lady of pleasure, once like her seat of <hi>Rome,</hi> the Empress of the World, <hi>Messallina</hi>'s or <hi>Faustina</hi>'s successor unto the <hi>Brothell</hi> house, A rare head of the Church that could n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>t chuse but be spotlesse and undefiled by such a conspicuous blemish in this female Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop. Stories are full of such prelates, as have accoutred themselves in Martial habiliments, and changed their Cro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sier staffe for a Spear and a Lance; but there is no such shamelesse record as of this she prelate, that changed Saint <hi>Peters</hi> Keys to Sciffers, and the Sword to a Distaffe; and because I am mentioning the absurdity thereof, it will not be amisse to shew the inconveniencies that atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded the Roman Catholick Religion, by this <hi>Joanes</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing admitted Pope.</p>
            <p>First, It will necessarily follow that the Church (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding as the papists Tenour is) once hopt headlesse; For
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:205881:8"/>the Church is defined by them to be a company of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>stian men professing one Faith; under one Head, to wit, the Pope; but she was no pope, for a Woman is not capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of Holy Orders, and could not play the pope; and secondly, That Church by reason of her, must not be ow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned as a true Church; for where the lawful orderly en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tire (without breach) succession of Bishops faileth, that cannot be a true Church, which the Roman Church suffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by reason of pope <hi>Joanes</hi> intervention betwixt <hi>Leo</hi> the Fourth, and <hi>Benedict</hi> the Third; this will hold against <hi>Baronius,</hi> and all assertors of the true succession of the Ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man Bishops, who reckon no interruption or <hi>interregnum</hi> thereof though they confesse, that many Apostates, rather then Apostolical persons, have occupied that Room; and that there have been many popes which came irregularly to the papacy, and served for no other purpose then Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phers in Arithmetick to make up number; Yet this one Woman pope spoyls the play and that pretence, for she cannot be reckoned any way to be Saint <hi>Peters</hi> successor, though we should grant the succession of
<note place="margin">a <hi>Chronol. lib.</hi> 4. <hi>sae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cul.</hi> 10. <hi>ad annum</hi> 904.</note> Fifty popes together, who came in unlawfully, and governed as madly.</p>
            <p>Thirdly, It being proved there was such a Pope, the po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pish priests may well doubt of the lawfulness of their mis<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>sion; and the Lay papists of the sufficiency of the absolu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, which the priests give <gap reason="illegible" resp="#keyers" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>on Ear Confessions, and of the Truth of the real presence and Transubstantiation; for unlesse the popish priests be priested by a lawfull Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>shop, their priesthood is not worth a Rush; unless the Lay papists be absolved by a lawful priest, their absolution is worth nothing: and unlesse the words of Consecration be uttered by a lawful priest, intent upon his business, there follows no substantial change in the Creatures of Bread and Wine. Now how can the priests be assured that they were priested by lawful Bishops: and how can Lay priests be assured that they are absolved by lawful priests, since we have seen, and they may when they please, that pope
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:205881:9"/>
               <hi>Joane,</hi> gave Orders, made Deacons, Priests, Bishops and Abbots: For it may be well enough that the priests of this present age, are descended from those who were ordained by her: especially seeing we no where read, that they were degraded by succeeding popes, who had their Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation from her. Not to mention that high prerogative of infallibility, which the popes pretend to, now resting in a frail seducible Woman, that could not tell so much as the time of her delivery; but so shamefully betrayed the infirmity and weaknesse of the Apostolical Chair.</p>
            <p>To conclude, all the Water in the River of <hi>Tyber</hi> will never wash off the pollution and stain, which the abomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of this Pope <hi>Joane</hi> hath stuck upon the pontificall Sanctity and Supremacy.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>